[Music]
hello and welcome to today's video in
today's video i'm going to be showing
you how we can give our scene a bit of a
refresh
just to take away those boring gold
spheres and put in these nice uh 3d
objects which is a free asset pack from
itch
see we've got them rotating to make them
just look a bit more visually appealing
we've got a cinemachine camera that's
following our little bean around and we
can come over here and we can pick up
the items
and the requested feature in the kind of
the main sort of point in this video is
that we can now drop them
onto the ground
and we can pick them back up
and all the same stuff so we can still
save our game
and load our game the stuff that we've
already picked up will be deleted it'll
go back into our inventory
and very importantly we are going to fix
a bug that i found while recording the
video with our unique id script
there was a bit of a kind of glaring
issue with that which i've since
fixed i hope fingers crossed but let's
just get straight into the video okay
let's just get started so we're here
with our um scene you know we've got our
kind of ballroom blobs on the ground and
if you go to the links in the
description
there's a free low poly 3d and pixel 2d
and pack which we can use here and just
click download now um
and then you can you know you can tip
them or you can just say no thanks take
me to the downloads and you can get a
load of models for free and you can see
some of the the models here so we're
going to use a couple of these to kind
of jazz up our scene once we've got that
all set up we will add um dropping items
out of the inventory and putting them
back on the ground so once you've
downloaded the um unity asset uh package
this unity package we can just drag and
drop that into our assets folder and
it's quite a big package so it'll take a
little bit of time so you see that it's
importing now and then once it's
imported it will bring up this unity
import package if i just make this a bit
bigger there's quite a lot of stuff in
here you can import the whole package if
you want and it's a bit unnecessary some
of the stuff we're not going to be using
but i'll leave that up to you
um
so i'm just going to collapse everything
when our list is open like that and it's
expanded if you hold alt and click the
top level it will collapse everything
inside it as well so i don't need the
readme and i don't need the reference
under here i'm just going to get the
ortho images
and then under 3d
we'll bring all of the 3d in
um because there is a series of prefabs
and we don't want to have to go through
and uncheck the ones that we don't want
uh we can just delete the ones we don't
want back out of our project if that's
the case
and you can see that in the um images
here for the offo view there's just
little renders of the images
um of the items inside and this is what
we'll use to display in our inventory so
just go ahead and hit import and again
depending on how many objects you've
picked in that menu it'll take a while
to bring all of these in okay so they're
all in now and you see that we've got
this new folder assets devil workshop
and we've got our 3d um folder and then
in prefabs we see our prefabs here and
we can drag in the chests for example
and we can see them here
there's different eggs and stuff but
let's just undo that
so what i'm actually going to do
first i'm going to come down here and
i'm going to delete all of our items
and i'll leave just one of them
and i think i've already set this as a
prefab
prefabs yes we've got our tomato here so
i'm just going to open up the prefab in
the prefab viewer and i'm going to
delete our sort of boring test sphere
and then let's go
to the devil's workshop prefab scene and
i'm actually going to drag in one of the
potions i'm going to drag in this health
potion here so let's just drag that
under our
tomato and you see here in the game view
that the prefab has updated so i'm going
to go back out into our scene go back to
our prefab here and i'm going to rename
it from tomato to health
potion and i'm going to click on our
tomato inventory item data here
and i'm going to rename this
to health potion let's call it health
poaching data just so we know exactly
what it is so now i'm going to change
the display name to health potion
description
this is a health potion
stack size and gold value we'll just
leave them as it is for now and then
let's go back to our 2d assets
come into the images folder and then
you're going to need to select
everything in this folder so click on
the top item hold down shift and click
on the bottom item and under texture
type swap that from default to sprite 2d
and ui and then we can just hit apply
and again depending on how many images
you've got in this folder this will take
a while so just let that complete okay
so they're all now sprite images so if
we go back over to our item data and
select our health potion we can now open
this up and we can find our potion so
we'll just type in potion
and you can see here that we've got a
nice icon for our potion
and i'm just going to rename the actual
prefab in the scene to health potion as
well and you'll see that if i hit play
now and we walk over the potion we have
our potion and it's gone in with the new
icon now you can see it's a little bit
stretched it doesn't look uh perfectly
good so let's fix that
um to do that we need to go into our um
into a few different scripts so
we can go over to canvas
inventory ui controller and let's start
with the player hotbar so let's open up
our static inventory display script so
we've got our script here i'm just going
to let this
open properly in rider okay so we
actually need to go to the inventory
slot ui script that was my mistake so
let's go through to there
so you can see here that we've got our
private image item sprite
what we need to do in uh on awake is we
need to go to
item sprite dot preserve um aspect and
just set that to true and in code the
reason for that and it's quite annoying
is if we go back into unity
and select one of our um
inventory slot uis
you can see when there's not a sprite in
there you can't see the preserve aspect
ratio
box
so we go to our image so there's no um
preserve aspect ratio box it's hidden
if we put a sprite in
you can see now it says
preserve
aspect but obviously we don't want to
have the graphics in because that's all
set through code and so we just need to
set that to true through code as well
and we need to do that in a couple of
other places as well so we need to do
this on the
mouse item data as well
so we'll come over to awake and we can
say
item
sprite dot
preserve aspect and just set that to
true so now if we go back in and we pick
up the item you see that the icon's not
stretched and then we can pick it up and
put it onto our mouse and it's not
stretched there
let's go over to our chest and we can
put it in our chest and it's not
stretched there okay so that's all
working and looking good i'm just going
to come over to our chest
and i'm going to delete these two cubes
and we need to open the prefabs i've
made a prefab of them so let's delete
those two cubes
let's go over to our 3d prefab scene and
we've got these um
cool chests so for the small chest i'm
gonna have these golden
this nice gold chest
um and then for the big chest we've
actually made a prefab of this but let's
delete our cubes from under that and
then i'm going to drag in the silver
chest
under our big chest item so you see
these are rotated slightly
um so i'm just going to rotate this
around just so the front latch is at the
front
and same again with this let's just
rotate that round
and then we'll have to override apply
our changes to this prefab and then i'm
actually going to make a prefab out of
this chest as well so let's just drag
our big chest in here so now we've got
that as a prefab so to make some other
items it's quite a simple process so
i'll do another one and then i'll go
through and do a time lapse of making
the others you can do
sort of yours in your own time
so let's just ctrl d and duplicate our
health potion and then i'm gonna
right click prefab unpack completely i'm
just going to call this one mana potion
underneath that will delete the um
bottle from it and let's actually just
drag this over
so let's go back to these assets and
this time i'm going to get the mana
potion
you can see that's there's a purple
liquid instead of a red liquid
actually just for differentiation i'll
drag in the poison bottle
and let's just rename this to
poison
potion just so they look a bit visually
different
on the item data let's select one of the
other data's that one of these temporary
data i'll select the apple um and then
i'll rename our apple to poison
potion data
we'll select the poison sprite so we've
got this sprite here
uh rename this to poison potion
this is a poison
potion
max stack size can be one um
and we've got a gold valley let's just
put 10. it doesn't really matter we
haven't got any sort of currency sort of
set up yet so we've got our health
potion and a poison potion
so i'm going to do two more different
item types using some of the prefabs in
here
so like i said i'll time-lapse that
and you can do as many or as few as you
want
okay so i've got our items here and i'm
just going to make some prefabs of them
so let's go back over to our prefabs
folder
and we'll select all of the ones that we
haven't made prefabs of and we'll just
drag them
so we have to drag them over here one by
one so let's drag in our poison potion
our cogs and our sword
and our health potion and i moved the
sort of
visual representation down so i'll just
apply those changes
so now you can see that we can add these
back into the scene
and we'll have to move them up slightly
so we can drag them out and position
them kind of around the scene how we
want and drag in another sword
so if we hit play now you can see that
there are they're a little bit boring um
they're just sort of stationary so let's
just add a bit of uh spin kind of
movement to them
so we can go over to our item script uh
item pickup
so this monobehaviour lives on the items
um
and what we can do is in the update
function we can do private void update
and in here we're just going to rotate
the items kind of over time
and we can put a speed in so we can do
serialize field private float
and then we'll do underscore um rotation
speed
and what we'll say is um we'll do
transform
dot
rotate
and we'll rotate around
vector 3 dot up and then we'll times
that by our
rotation speed and then times by time
dot delta time and then let's set our
rotation speed to uh let's see 20 let's
see whether that's too fast or not
so you can see that all of our health
potions now have this rotation speed
um let's set it to 20 in the inspector
as well and just hit play let's see what
that looks like so you see that our
items are just slowly rotating um
on the ground i've missed
these items up here
let's drag them under our
items and we'll put a rotation speed of
20 in there okay so that's just a little
bit more visually interesting like while
they're on the ground we can run over
and pick them up they're in our
inventory we've got our potions let's
split them come over here let's make
sure everything's going to save so let's
put some potions in this chest
we've got this bigger chest here let's
put our stacked potions in there and one
of our swords
let's save our game come back out hit
play
load our game and you can see that all
of our items are back in their
respective spots we've got our sword and
potions and our potions there so that's
still good that's still working so now
let's make it so we can actually drop
the items on the ground
from our inventory so if i go over to
our mouse item data script
you can see here that we've got this um
we've got this thing in the update
function that just says uh if the
mouse.current.left button was pressed
this frame and we're not over a ui
object currently we just delete the item
by clearing the slot but we have we've
had this to do here for quite a while no
minutes to drop the item on the ground
so let's get rid of the and to do and
let's actually do it so let's just make
some space up here
um and i'm actually going to
up here let's make a private transform
variable and we'll just call this the
player
transform
and in awake i'm just going to
cache our player so i'm going to do
player transform
is equal to
game object dot find
oh
that's game
object with a capital g
find object
game object with tag and we'll just put
in the tag of player
and then we'll do dot get component and
we'll get there transform component and
we'll cache that
now you may have a reference to your
player somewhere else like on your game
manager should get them from that way um
this is just like a quick and dirty way
to get the player transform
and i'm just gonna if
player
transform is equal to null then let's
dot log um player not found and that's
just in case you know something happens
we'll see um that that's an issue so
let's go back to our project and let's
select our player and let's make sure
that they have the player tag we need to
make sure they've got that okay so we're
back in our mouse item data script and
we need to instantiate our item here
when we click it but we need to
know what exactly we need to instantiate
so for that we're going to need to add
another variable on our inventory item
data so let's go over here
and let's make a public
game object
and we'll just call this um
item prefab
and then we can go back over to our
mouse item data here
and we can say um instantiate
our assigned inventory slots dot item
data dot item prefab
and where we want to instantiate it is
we want to do the player.transform but
we need to position it somewhere kind of
in front of the player or to the side of
the player if we do it exactly where the
player is we'll just pick the item
straight back up
which is a bit of a pain so we can do
player.transform dot forward and then we
can just put in a bit of a like a drop
offset um i'm just gonna put one f we
can change that if we need to and we
could make this a variable if we wanted
to
um so we can control it in the inspector
but one f should be fine uh as long as
the distance is
is greater than kind of where the radius
of the item pickup is so we've got um
we'll put that just forward and then
we'll do katrinian.identity
and then we can clear the slot
and what you may want to do is just
check um
this so
if uh item prefab is not equal to null
then instantiate it and then we can
clear the slot
ah okay this is my mistake sorry we need
to drop it um
at the player transform
dot
dot position
plus
the player transform dot forward times
to buy the drop drop offset because we
need to kind of attach it to where the
player is and then just add a little bit
of distance in front of the player so
that was my mistake let's try that again
pick this up and then we can drop it out
of our inventory okay we've picked that
straight back up so now let's put this
back to one
hopefully that won't that'll be a bit
better let's pick it up drop it
nope still picking it up so let's put
this two
three
pick it up
drop it okay there you go it's uh in
front of the player now so we see a
couple of issues here so it's in the
floor um and it's not rotating
and that's because i changed the
rotation speeds here but i didn't apply
them um to the prefab so we just need to
hit apply all
so let's just hit ok to that message
okay so that that should sort that if we
look now all of our items have a
rotation speed of 20 and we can see that
the problem was that the item was
spawning kind of on the ground and the
actual pivot is here
so there are a couple of ways to solve
this
and the easiest would probably be to
open up all of our um
items and let's select the actual
game objects within them
let's just move them back up
if we look kind of where the radius of
the pivot is so now
so this pivot is actually going to be
where the potion spawns on the ground
so let's just move them up slightly a
little bit more okay so we've moved them
up now let's get our poison
uh get the top level prefab objects
and we've got our sphere collider here
which we're setting its radius we can
just move this up off the ground as well
by raising the y axis
so now
the actual collider is around the game
object but the pivot is slightly below
so if we go back to these top level
items
of our prefabs we've got the potion the
cogs and the
um
sword
i don't think the cogs moved up
annoyingly so let's just move them up
properly let's move them a little bit
more to kind of like there
so let's apply those changes to our
prefabs and we'll see that the other
items should sort themselves out as well
so we'll hit apply and there you go all
of our prefabs have updated
and now we can select all of the items
in the world and we can actually reset
their uh
axis on the y
okay so they're all on the ground now
but they're floating um so let's go back
in
and we'll pick them up
and then we can pick them up and drop
them out of our inventory
and i made the changes to the mouse
object in play mode so just make sure
you set that not in play mode come back
over pick them all up and then hopefully
finally we'll be able to pick it up and
drop it kind of in front of us and it
spins and we can pick it back up
so currently if we pick up our three
potions and drop them on the ground just
one potion will be dropped uh not all
three so let's sort that out
so instead of clearing the slot uh what
we can actually do is we can say
um
if
assigned oh wait is the game still
running no okay let's get rid of that so
if assigned inventory slot dot item data
dot um stack
uh not data assigned inventory start dot
stack size
is
greater than one
then we want to do something
else
we can clear the slot
because they'll be the last item
so instead of clearing the slot if
there's more than one item on the
item prefab what we actually want to do
is we want to take our assigned
inventory slot and
we can um add to stack
and we're actually going to add minus
one so that'll take one away
and then we can call our update um we
can call our update mouse slot function
and i'm actually going to make a version
of this method that doesn't take
anything in
so let's get rid of this
and then get rid of that
and here i'm going to call update mouse
slot
and here we don't need to assign imagery
slots we're going to do it here
so let's get rid of that and then
instead of taking from our items this
inventory slot that we passed in
because we've already assigned it we can
just pop it in here
um and we can make that private because
we're not i don't know we may we may
call that from somewhere else in the
future who knows so we'll just leave
that public and then we've got our
update function here so it's going to
take one away from the stack and then
it'll update the actual ui to show that
and we'll spawn it on the ground so
let's pick this up
so we've got three health potions we can
pick it up and we can drop one so we've
got two left in our mouse we can do it
again
okay you'll notice a bit of an issue
here with our unique id script which i
didn't actually catch earlier so that's
good we can we can debug this so we've
got our unique id script and what it
seems to be doing is it's um spawning it
with the id from the prefab
because that's what we've we
have assigned it to in the prefab so we
need to update our
um
unique id script
okay so that was a bit of a pain um i've
had to do some jiggery pokery of the
unique id script i think it's working
i've tested you know starting the editor
closing the editor starting it up again
changing scenes
and building and running the game making
a save in the built version again
loading it back up in the editor making
a save in the editor or the built
version of the game and it seems to be
working it's quite robust
um
if you do have any problems or you know
any better way of doing this do let me
know in the comments uh
i'd love to make sure this is kind of
like production ready and we could
actually use this properly
um but for now i'll just go over some of
the changes that i've made so you can
see that i've got rid of the onvalidate
function and i've actually generated
and i've changed it to the awake
function
um the private string i've got rid of
the generating guide there
the reason for that is that it doesn't
need to be called because we're checking
and generating a key here anyway um if
it needs to be and the reason we don't
need on validate and we can actually use
awake
it's because of the execute in edit mode
um tag on the script this attribute here
so this is gonna work in the same sort
of way as um
on validate wood when we generate a new
item like duplicate an item or drag it
out the inspector it will do the right
checks and it will generate it
something else that's worth noting is um
i'm initializing it here
but there were some instances where it
wouldn't actually be initialized the
database would would be void for some
reason and so i'm just checking if
in a way just doing a null check to see
whether the database has actually been
initialized if it hasn't we'll just
create a new database so that's just
this bit of code here but we're putting
it here instead and then this is the
same as what was on in the unvalidate
function so if the database contains the
id already
then let's generate a new id
and if it doesn't contain it let's add
it to it and then in on destroy we're
just saying that if the database
contains the key
let's just remove our id
and then generate i've not changed that
that's the same and the only other thing
i've changed for this script then is
over on item pickup
i've moved the id get component unique
id into star instead of on awake
the reason for this is that we are
generating
the id in the unique idea wake so if
this script gets called after
this awake function
then the
id wouldn't be ready it wouldn't have
been generated then if we tried to add
it um
it wouldn't work it wouldn't have
generated and it wouldn't have um
there was no guarantee that it would
have been unique because it may have
been
the same sort of id before we actually
generated a new one
so we can go back over to uni we can see
this kind of working so if i hit play
everything's going to be working the
same so if i pick up all of these
so i've got three cogs two potions two
swords
i can drop my potions and you can see
over in the console there's no sort of
errors
this was just a test over in the unique
id script
um
just debug.logging the actual count of
the database when we generate it i was
just making sure that was working
um but you can see we've got two potions
here and we can pick them back up and we
got two potions and we can drop them
again and there's no sort of uh errors
there
and we do the same with the cogs we can
pick up the cogs and we can drop some
cogs and we can um every time it
generates a new id you can see that
we're getting the count of the database
when we pick it up so there's eight and
nine if we pick up the items and then
drop them again you see that you know
it's obviously reducing them as we're
picking it's obviously reducing the
database count as we pick up items and
then generating new ones when we spawn
them back in if it needs to
the first one that we drop will have the
same unique id as the
prefab but that's fine um you know as
long as it's unique that's okay
so we can pick up all of our items
okay hit save come out of the game go
back into the game
and then when we hit load because we've
already picked up these items they will
delete themselves
and then we can come over here and we
can put some stuff in the chests
let's split this cog stack hit save come
back out and then if we run the game so
we'll build and run and we can hit load
they'll delete we've had them we've got
our hotbar we have our cogs let's add
them we have our potions to take on them
split the stack keep that there
and there you have it so that should all
be working like i said if you've got any
issues with this unique id script
do let me know i'll carry on doing some
experiments with it as well and see if i
can break it and if i do i'll fix it
okay so the last little change i want to
make is i want to come up here and i
want to add
a cinemachine
camera so let's go to window
package manager
and let's go to the unity registry and
look for cinemachine and let's just
install this package
so we've seen the machine installed
let's just come up to cinemachine we'll
create a virtual camera
and i'll put it at the kind of spot that
our camera was at so i'm just going to
reset everything to zero
and then in our camera i'm going to drag
our player into the follow and i'll drag
our player into the look at as well
and then we can move our camera up
slightly and kind of position it into
sort of the perspective that we want for
our player then under binding mode i'm
just going to do a sim uh i'm going to
swap that to world space and then i'm
going to
select do nothing on the aim
so you see that if we hit play now as we
walk along the camera will follow our
player
um around the scene so we can uh
make it a little bit more dynamic as
we're walking around and we're accessing
this stuff
but yeah there we have it ended up being
a bit more long-winded than i was hoping
because of that bug but you know it's
good that we caught it and we can kind
of correct that so i said the project
files for this video are over on my
patreon which is patreon.com forward
slash danpos i'd just like to take a
minute to thank my supporters in the 10
000 xp tier we have omega mike and on
screen now are all the amazing 4 000 xp
tier patrons if you've been enjoying the
series so far it'd be great if you could
hit the like button it really helps the
channel out and if you've got this far
through without subscribing it'd be
great if you could hit the subscribe
button as well in the meantime thanks
for watching and i'll see you in the
next one bye
you